Good evening. It is time for another edition of What Would Your Ancestors Say? This is something
that I started a couple weeks ago to start bringing folks into the world of What Would
The Ancestors Say? And so before we even begin, I want to just show you all what I got coming up
so that you can be a part of it if you want to. I don't know why this did this like this.
Why is it range? Source in and out. Okay. So I'm really looking forward to bringing you the book
and the one woman show, What Would The Ancestors Say? Which I've been developing for a year and it
has finally gotten to a point of refinement where I really am ready to bring it to you all on another
level. So the book, the book drops on November 8th. This book was completely written, was designed,
was illustrated by me. The LA show is not sold out. Yeah. Where'd you get that idea?
The LA show is not sold out. It's not even showing up as sold out on the website.
Yeah. So if you go to amandalandexports.com, the link is right here. If you go to amandalandexports.com,
you can get your tickets to either watch the live stream or you can get the live stream plus a
signed copy of the book. Or you can get tickets to be in the in-studio audience in Los Angeles.
So all these tickets are available and I hope to see you at the show, which is coming up on November
8th. And also I hope that you will get the book when the book drops on November 8th. So yeah,
I mean, it's, it's, so tonight we will begin, we will continue our series of What Would Your Ancestors
Say, where I speak to different people who come on the live about who, I speak to different people
on the live about who they consider their ancestors to be, about what they feel their ancestors would
say about where we are now, about where they are now, et cetera. So, uh, let me give you a sneak
peek. Sister Seals, this is your ancestor, Harriet Tubman. I tell her, I was MC Check-a-hole,
but now I'm your father. Oh, chill baby, chill. It helps her go to sleep. It helps her go to sleep.
The Divide and Conquer is also about keeping you apart from your soul. It's also no coincidence that
some of our greatest icons of liberation made Palestine an incredibly important part of their
platform. So, uh, head on over to Amanda Land Exports or AmandaSeals.com and you can get your tickets
and you can also get, uh, the signed book with your tickets. However, you won't be able to get, like,
the book by itself until November 8th. All right, without further ado, let's get into,
uh, and I hope, I hope to see people getting tickets while we're on here. I hope to see people
getting tickets while we're on here. Hmm. Now there is going to be an audible or, uh, an audio book
version, but not immediately. All of these things cost money and take time. And so, you know, it's, um,
it's a process. And when you're doing things independent, baby,
because you know, like that, that promo that you just saw, like I edited that.
Okay. And I know that some people were like, but why do you do everything yourself? Because
you know, it's, it's cheaper. And, um, I don't know, at this point it kind of keeps me closer to
the work. I can't keep it up, but it was, it's been a very necessary aspect to being,
to resetting from, from leaving the Hollywood space. Um, also want to remind you that I will
be doing a book tour. Okay. So the book tour launches on the 6th in San Diego, and we are still
putting it together. We are looking for spaces that don't have to be black owned. They don't have to be,
um, a bookstore. It literally just needs to be a space that is people power. This is not a dress
or a shirt. It is a jumpsuit. So, uh, we are in the process of looking for spaces, particularly in
Delaware and Baltimore, um, and Detroit really need to find a space in Detroit, like yesterday. Um,
so do I enjoy the marketing and editing sometimes, but it's like a different mind. So I have to like
go into a different space. You know what I mean? Uh, someone asked, what does the book get into?
What would the ancestors say is the text of my one woman show? What would the ancestors say? And it
talks about everything from the here, nigga, damn laws. So you got to see it to see what that's about.
Uh, it also talks about, um, you know, what would Harriet Tubman say? Like if she came back here,
it also talks about the, uh, the realities around Juneteenth. It talks about the connectivity between
black Americans and Palestinians, et cetera, et cetera, et cetera. And so what I feel like is really
interesting about this is that if you are somebody that's more of a thinker than a reader,
it allows you to really like get into some really thoughtful, deep ideas and concepts very quickly,
and then allows you to get your mind going and moving and zooming and ju- and, and, and, and, and, uh,
and ju-king, right? So it's not the kind of book like, uh, Noam Chomsky. No, it's creative,
it's art, but it also is looking at our world through that lens. All right. So who wants to
come up tonight and talk about their, um, ancestors? Who wants to come up tonight and talk about their
ancestors? So we've got people that have requested to join. So, uh, let's see. Remember, if you request
to join, I might call on you. Cause what happens is people come up like, ah, I didn't know.
Moss AI said, I worry you're not loving yourself enough. You don't have to worry about me. Not
about that. I'm fine. Arliss Michaels. What is good? Okay. So this person is not coming up.
Okay. Let's see. Rhiannon, you know the dark. Oh, yes. You're on right now.
Why do y'all do this to me? Why? I think I made it. Hi. Wait. Okay. I think I have two people on.
Who's who? I'm Donna. I'm Rhiannon. Okay. Who wants to talk about their ancestors?
She can go. Oh, thank you so much. My ancestors. Okay. I'm going to remove you, Rhiannon.
I'll see you in Morrisville. Yes, please.
So my ancestors, my ancestors came from Syria, Lebanon. And what I found out as an, in my thirties
is that my father was adopted. And so all of my life, I thought I was half Syrian, half Lebanese,
but it turns out I'm half Eastern European as well, probably Ashkenazi. So, so, so for me,
it's been, you know, a journey that I didn't expect. But I'm here and am I, you know, I'm,
I'm okay with it. I just wonder who I would have been had I had, was in touch with that other side
of the family throughout my life, because I've been an activist and an advocate since, you know,
I'm a teenager. I, I, I, I marched against the Vietnam War. I marched against apartheid in South
Africa. I went to South Africa to study truth and reconciliation. I've been to occupied Palestine
four times. I did my PhD on that topic. Wow. And, you know, I actually sat across Palestinians
trying to survive in their historic homeland and ask them questions that they were never asked
before in their lives. Like, how would you resolve this? What are your hopes? What are your dreams?
And, and, and so I was dealing with people who had no concept of being asked those questions,
because no one's ever asked them, they tell them where the what they're supposed to do. So,
so my ancestors, you know, I've been to the village where my my great grandfather came from in Syria.
And I'm very in touch with my culture. And I'm proud of my culture. And most of what I do
surrounds that culture. Um, so, uh, my ancestors, I'm trying to, I mean, I hope my ancestors are happy
with me. Because you know what I work, I've worked very hard throughout my life to be, um, you know,
someone who's been involved in social change and, and human and civil rights actions. And, um, I continue
to do that at age 71. So, yes, ma'am, I'm 71. I'm getting over COVID right now. So I don't look too
cute. But I can, I can, I can do it, you know, I can, I can make myself look a lot better. But right
now, I'm kind of just laying in bed talking to you. Um, but, you know, coming on when you are in the
midst of getting over COVID. Lord, yes, yes. And I want to tell you something that I am so
in awe of you. I am so appreciate what you do. And, you know, I feel like, um, I don't know if
enough people tell you that, but, but you need to keep doing what you're doing. And, um, I just,
I just think you're wonderful and smart. And, and your commentary is always on point. I'm always like,
100% agree. I'm always typing that. And I continue to do that. But I think you're wonderful. And I don't
care about the haters. I don't care about the people who are negative. They don't know what
the hell is going on. Okay. Because they're not aware that they're following, you know, the BS
news reports that we get. I don't watch mainstream media. You know, I, I get my reports from over
there. I I've been on in 2016, I went on a delegation to Syria. It was a fact finding dedication,
uh, uh, uh, delegation with the U S peace council. And we came back and gave a report to the UN
because we wanted to see, was it a civil war or was it a proxy war? And it was clear that it was a
proxy war. Okay. But you know, you were there, you just, you were there for a day and you realized
that all the stuff that our media has been telling us didn't make sense. It wasn't logical.
You know, I actually was a group that we met with Assad for two hours. He spoke to us. Yes. And
he let us ask him anything. Now, you know, he wasn't perfect. There's a lot of, there's a lot
of issues and problems, but it didn't take me long to figure out as I figured out in going to occupied
Palestine since 2008, I've been there four times. I think I said that, that everything that we've been
told is BS. And, you know, um, I can, I spend part of my day every day, a large part of my day,
sharing information, trying to educate people and trying to help people see that what they've
been told or what they believed is not, it's not okay. You've been manipulated. Don't you want the
truth? I want the truth. I'm still mad that they taught me about Thanksgiving the way they did when I
was in, when I was in grammar school, you know, I mean, don't lie to me. Tell me the truth because
I have the ability to critically and analyze facts if they're facts. But if you're, if you're just
trying to manipulate me, I'm not okay with it. So, you know, I might be unusual because I have visited
the places that I was interested in finding out about. And I think, I think that's so important
though in, in, you know, disseminating between who's talking theory and who's talking actuality,
right? I mean, so many of us are really just over here. And I will say that in this latest
iteration of violence against the Palestinians since October 7th, for many people, it was the
first time that they got to actually speak directly to Palestinians, right? And so that really shifted
a lot of the mindset for folks. Um, and it really opened the aperture for folks, but people like
you are like, I've been there four times. Yeah. Yeah. 2012, I was in Gaza doing my PhD work
and my research. And, you know, I walked around looking at that place and if this was after the
settlers had been pulled out, this was after, you know, all the buildings the settlers had been in
were knocked down. They talk about how, oh, we left the buildings and we left them. No, they didn't.
They knocked them all down. They destroyed everything. There were no greenhouses left.
The Palestinians are farmers and they were growing some of the most beautiful, wonderful produce.
But I walked around looking and I saw that beach. And in my mind, I said, if this beach was anywhere
else in the world, it would be an international destination. And people would be, I mean, it was,
it was just truly beautiful. It was pristine and beautiful. But I also knew that the Israelis would
never allow the Palestinians to benefit from it. So all this BS about how they could have built it
up and we didn't, we, you know, we weren't occupying. Yes, they were. Well, I was there.
They, they, you know, they drove, wrote it and they murdered a little boy who was playing football
in his yard. And, and, you know, I was there the last night I was there, they started bombing.
So I lived through one night of that. I left there with, I had PTSD for over a year from that. And can
you, and then I watched these people and now I have people that I know and love there because I've met
them. And, and, you know, I have personal relationships. So, um, you know, this for me has
been life changing and I will never be the same again. None of us will, none of us will. We have
witnessed a genocide in real time. And, you know, I'm in touch with people who, you know,
who tell me what's going on. And that's, you know, those relationships are very important.
And everyone, you know, a lot of people could have those relationships because of Facebook,
you know, and, and all of that, but I maintain those and our people in the West Bank too. I mean,
you know, Tulka Room is under siege. Uh, uh, uh, you know, they, they just,
they try to take our attention and they put us elsewhere and then they go into the other spot
and they mess everybody up. You know, I mean, it's just, I know women who had to give birth
during this horrible genocide, you know, with, you know, obviously the hospital conditions were
bad. They, they were afraid to leave their homes to go to the hospital to have their babies
because they could be shot. Same thing in the West Bank, same thing in the West Bank. So I love you.
And I'm just so happy that I have had the opportunity to have this conversation with you.
I'm so happy. People in the chat are like, thank you for adding her. And thank you so much for
sharing and being so honest about your ancestry, about your experiences in Gaza and in the West Bank
and in, um, and in Palestine. And really just as always, I appreciate anybody who is, you know,
who's, who feels like it is their responsibility to educate and to share, because I feel like so
many people just are, you know, kind of laissez-faire about that. But I, I'm the same way as you. I'm
like, no, if I know, then you have to know. That's right. And I'm frustrated if you don't get it. You
know, when I try to explain something to people and they go, well, you know, it's, I don't know
enough. It's just too complicated. No, it's not. It's not complicated. They wanted you to think it
was, but it's not, it's not. And I believe that we are put on this earth to help other people.
And, and so, you know, um, I feel a kinship with you. That's even stronger now. And I just love it.
I think it's great. I think it's great. And I hope that, you know, I hope to come back again some
other time and, you know, and communicate with you because you're wonderful. With the lights on
when you feel better. I know. I don't want you to see what I look like. No, no, no. I'm glad you're
getting over COVID. We're all like, hey, we get it. Next time I'll do my hair and I'll put a little
makeup on and some lipstick. Okay. What is your Instagram? What's your handle? I don't have, I have
no idea. My name is Donna Nassar, N-A-S-S-O-R. I'm 71. I'm lucky I can get on Instagram and figure
out. You guys, it's one word. D-O-N-N-A-N-A-S-S-O-R. Correct. Okay. Correct. So I will add that because
people want to follow you. So thank you, Donna. That's so beautiful. God bless you. Thank you
so much, honey. I really appreciate it. Have a good night. I appreciate you. Good night. Thanks.
You guys make me feel so good about the community that I managed to build here at Instagram because
at one point in time, y'all, at one point in time, it was like, I don't know.
I don't know about this place. I don't know. If you're just joining us, it is another edition
of what would, what would your ancestors say? And we are here talking to people about their
ancestors, about who they think their ancestors are, about what their ancestors would say about
where we are in the world. And this is all to lead up to the book release and live stream
performance of my show. What would the ancestors say? Which is happening November 8th, live
from LA. You can support my work by getting tickets to the live stream. You also have a
package there where you can get the live stream and a signed copy of the book. What would the
ancestors say? And you can also, if you're in Los Angeles, get a ticket to be in the building.
So you'd be able to get, uh, you get a ticket to the show, plus you get the book, plus you'll
get a meet and greet signed book and a photo. So we have all of this going on. And, um, this
is, you know, this is a part of my independent entertainment work that I'm doing. And remember
everything was done by me. So you've got the book, you've got the illustrations. Uh, we've
got, I love the forward that I put in here. Um, and so all of that is happening and I'm
just really excited that you guys are going to get to see this, this project comes to the
next level. So let's bring the next person on to talk about their ancestors.
So let's see. All right. We're bringing on someone named Travis Sankofa. Travis Sankofa.
Let's see. Travis. Are you there? I am. Can you hear me? All right, Travis, where are you,
where are you talking to us from? I'm talking to you from Minneapolis, Minnesota. Minneapolis,
Minnesota. They don't play around too much in Minneapolis. Okay. They burnt down a police
precinct. Um, so Travis, tell us about your ancestors. Who are they? Do you know who they
are? What do you think they would say about where we are?
Okay. Let me find a quiet spot to do that.
Okay. So while you are finding a quiet spot, think about it. Oh, you're ready. You're ready.
Okay. All right. I think I got it. Um, so my folks are from, I'm from Georgia. Okay. By the way. Um,
so I'm not a Minnesotian. Um, very proud Georgian. Um, you know, I think my ancestors would be,
um, um, that's a deep question because I, I recently did my ancestry DNA not too long ago
and, um, found some family that left the South some years ago and went to, um, Aliquippa, Pennsylvania.
Uh, so I'm from Blake, I'm from Blakely, Georgia, which is Southwest of, um, Atlanta. Okay.
And, um, um, we related to Whitney Houston down the line, um, and our family. That's where her folks
left and doing a great migration, migrated to New Jersey. Wow. Um, I'm also related.
So when she said, I believe the children are our future, you were the children of the future.
Oh man. Um, that is true. That is true. Um, let's see. Uh, I'm out,
Pleasure P is also my cousin. Um,
As in pretty Ricky Ricky Ricky. Yup. Yup. Yup. Yup. Yup. Yup.
Yup. Yup. Yup. Yup.
It's five in the morning.
That is, um, that is true. Um, I don't know if you know Bella Black. I'm also related to Bella Black.
She is in, um, Bella's in, I think she's going to be in P Valley. Yeah. Um, her album is out now.
Dirt Rose, too. You better, you better put on for your, your, uh, family members.
I got it. I got it. You see the album is out, y'all. They look black.
Yeah. Yeah. And their book. The book is out, too. Dirt Rose. Um, I got it. I got a dope,
dope family. Dope family. And I'm very proud of my ancestors. And I think
at this juncture of our existence, I think they would be
concerned. I think they would be concerned about,
um, where we're headed, but I also believe that they would be, uh, resilient as always,
considering what my folks have gone through, um, uh, living in, in Southwest, as we say, 229
in rural Georgia, um, and then making the, there you go. Um, but I think they would be as,
as resilient as, um, they've always been. And I think they would be as forthright as you
were when you debated those young folks.
Man, them people. Um, absolutely.
So when you did your genealogy, what actually made you say it's time to do?
Oh, it's kind of freezing up on me. I lost some of that.
When you did your, um, genealogy, what made you decide to go and get it done now?
You know, I've always wanted to know where my ancestors came from in Africa. That was the driving,
factor. Um, did it get that specific?
It only did in terms of country. And so I found like Cameroon, Nigeria, Bantu,
uh, very broad terms, but it didn't get into depth in terms of, um, any specific tribe. Yeah.
Okay. And so did you get any other surprises?
Um, so I'm assuming you did it through like a website.
Yep. Yep.
So they, it's, uh, ancestry DNA. They sent the tube, then you spit into the tube, put it
back in the seal, send it off.
You should consider since you have, um, American lineage that you, that you are actually aware
of, you could probably get, um, not probably you could, a genealogist would help get you like specifics
about like your actual American ancestors, like the jobs they held. Um, you know, like, even like,
if they were married more than once, et cetera, et cetera. Like, I find that stuff to be so
interesting because those genealogists, they're looking through archives. So they're looking
through like, you know, obituaries and all types of stuff. So they're able to paint an even like
more clearer picture of the people who came from you. I just saw the ancestry said there's some
update. I don't want to know. I don't want to know what the update is.
So you did one too. I did one years and years ago before I knew they were selling our data.
But you know, what you gonna do? So what kind of ancestor would you want to be for those coming
after you for the future Whitney Houston's reincarnated in your line? Oh, wow. Wow.
What kind of ancestor would I want to be? Um, you know, I'm a proud father of three. Awesome. Um,
what kind of ancestor would I want to, that is an amazing
question. You know, I, I would want to be an ancestor that was considerate of, and I think about
the, um, the indigenous populations, I think seven generations deep. Um, I would want to be an,
I would want to be an ancestor that was mindful. I would want to be an ancestor that was
considerate of what I put into myself because I knew that one day it would bear fruit. Um,
I would be, I would want to be an ancestor that, that, um, didn't kowtow to oppression and that,
um, someone that hopefully, um, those who come for me will look back and be proud to say,
you know, I come from that person, you know, I'm related. That person is my ancestor.
Can you, um, speak more to people about the people here about what that seven generations
from the indigenous people is, because some people may not know what that's about. And I would love
for you to just expound a little more. Yeah. So, um,
um, I think it is. And so in Minnesota, we have the Anishinaabe, um, and you have the Lakota people,
uh, Lakota, Lakota, Nakota, both, all three of me, I think friend or ally. Um, but in their tradition,
they talk about when they have their meetings and their plannings and their, uh, or what we would call
in doubles in West Africa. Hold on, pause. You are so black. Was that a, was that a fire alarm
beep that we all heard? You are so black. Why you gotta, why you gotta put my business in the street?
Y'all, this man is an African-American. Oh man. We all heard it. We all heard it.
Okay. Sorry, you was getting deep. And then that beep said, beep.
But I don't think nobody heard it, but you. All of us heard it. Everybody heard it. Because that is
a true sign of blackness in America, that that beep is gonna beep. And we get, I don't know why we,
I don't know why it doesn't bother us, but it'd be happening. Yeah. Because I tuned it out. I didn't,
I didn't even think about it until you said it. I love it so much. The authentic,
it's a T. Okay. So Lakota, Lakota, Dakota, they all mean friend and in their meetings when they're
planning. Their culture and their customs, they, they think generations, uh, seven generations deep.
Yes. Um, so every decision is made with, uh, at least the seventh generation in mind.
That is so, I mean, I find it so fascinating how within this concept of American values, like,
you know, they always talk about like American values, American values. I'm like, I don't even
know what that really means. Um, other than oppression and segregation, et cetera, because that to me is
values. Right. Because that, that, that is governing how you're, that's not just like how you individually
live. Like that's how your whole society operates. And it makes you think every time about how is this
going to, you know, impact, I mean, seven generations. And, um, it's so dope when I hear people
connecting to indigenous wisdom at this, at this phase, because particularly because my thing that
I've been trying to tell people lately is like, whatever the United States has told you,
you shouldn't pay attention to, you should make it your business to learn about. And they did so much
work to delegitimize and to, you know, try and sequester indigenous knowledge as savagery or lacking
civility when the truth be told, they were far more civil and, um, and visionary than any of these
people. Absolutely. Absolutely. Than any of these people. And you find that, of course, globally amongst
aboriginal and indigenous people. Um, you find a way of living in harmony with nature, even though we had
our faults and shortcomings, um, not that we were angelic and all of a sudden Europeans showed up
and we lost everything. But in reality too, that was a sense of communalism, a sense of humanity, a sense of, um,
responding to encroachment with purpose and not necessarily with a sense of savagery where, um,
you know, it's all or nothing and outright brutality. And of course you could point to the Mongols
in the Eurasian Peninsula having a sense of savagery. Um, but at the same time, in addition to that,
you do find a sense of normalcy coming into being and play once they embraced Islam.
And not that I'm a Muslim, but speaking realistically to the history of, of that time period. Um,
you know, we get the word mogul from some sense of normalcy that we're able to, that was able to set in,
uh, once Northern India and India of course became conquered and subdued, but nevertheless,
you find people settling into some sense of, uh, civilization.
Okay. So y'all, I don't know if you noticed, but Travis just flexed on us, uh, with a bunch of knowledge.
No, no, no.
Yes. Travis, where, where did you get all this knowledge? Where does this, um, interest and
curiosity and history come from? My, from my ancestors. They go full circle.
Touche.
Touche, my brother. Touche. All right. All right. You know, I, I always ask questions like that because,
um, I think some people feel like somebody has to be a professor or they have to be like in a certain,
you know, um, profession to learn beyond their, beyond the limitations of their own experience,
right? Or of their own ancestry. But hearing you talk about, you know, the, the global context of
things, I think it's so necessary for us to have that context, to understand our own individual
context, to understand the context of our own individual ancestry and existence.
Right. No doubt. Cause we're not disconnected from, from our ancestors. Right. Um, I think,
you know, it has a sense of separation, uh, a sense of I-ness. I think that we have inherited,
of course. Um, and I think that's what we've lost as a people is that connection and not totally,
but in some regard, that connection to, you know, I'm a part of something and not just out here floating
as, um, just an individual in the world. And of course that's a Western ideal.
Truth and facts. Um, so my last question is how did you come up with, or why is your Instagram name
Travis Sankofa? So my name is Travis. Um, and part of me wanting to reconnect with my ancestors and find my
history, uh, was a part of me releasing the name of Smith with some Travis Smith in terms of government.
Um, but the Sankofa came on because I was looking back and trying to move forward with getting a sense of
where I came from. Um, and so the Sankofa part became an addition to what my mother chose to name me,
which was Travis. Um, my spiritual system is called Wussam. Um, and Wussam is a custom and tradition
that I developed for my children and my family. Um, when I became a father 23 years ago, my oldest
child is 23. Um, my biggest fear was being deceived of who God is. And so I developed this system called
Wussam, W-U-S-E-M. Uh, it's a word that I created. Um, I took the letters W, S, and M. And everywhere I
traveled around the world, I noticed that human beings built with wood, stones, and metals.
And so I took the W for wood, the S for stone, and the M for metals. Um, my wife was born in Guam.
Her father is, um, African American from the United States. He was in the military.
Uh, but when her and I got together 31 years ago, we went to Guam. Well, it wasn't 31 years
ago that we went to Guam. But when I first went to Guam, we were driving and I was noticing that they
were building with wood, stones, and metals. And so the concept of self-development and growth and
development, um, I wanted to use the wood, stone, and metal as a metaphor. And as we did in our ancient
languages, we would insert vowels where necessary and, um, consonants when necessary. And so, um,
I added in the U and the, um, the E and came up with this word Wussam. Um, and the meaning that I gave
it was, what's your story? And so when I became a father, I ended up writing a creation story in a
book based on this concept of Wussam. Um, I figured no one knows what the beginning was. And so the creation
story in the book of Wussam begins by saying shortly after the beginning, and then I go into this narrative.
Um, I developed the word Tuzazi for my children. So we greet each other with Wussam, and then the
response is Oumu. Um, Oumu is the word that we give to the divine. And then the word that we use
in parting is the word Tuzazi, which is the word that I also created. So that's our word for love.
Um, and so Travis Sankofa becomes, um, my response to not knowing who my ancestors
were, where they came from, and what our indigenous tongue or language traditions, customs, and history
was. And so that is, um, a long-winded response to your question. I apologize.
Um, I have the book. I just haven't, uh, I got books everywhere. Like I, uh, I got a home full
of books, but my own. No, like, have you written a book about Wussam? I absolutely have. I just
haven't, I haven't published it yet, but, um, I have. Yeah, absolutely. What are you waiting for?
Um, you know, I refer to it as an internal autobiography, because you get to see my
transformation from a 15-year-old young man thinking about this. And, um, every year I
wrote a different chapter. And so my children would get to go back and actually relive this
journey of my growth and development, hence my Wussam. And they have their own Wussam. Um,
and so, yeah, I have. One day it's coming. Travis. Yes, ma'am. Brother. Listen, everybody
here is like, who is this man? Like, because you came on here very casual, and then you had
a whole universe existing within you that you're aware of. Because that's the thing. All of us
have this universe within us, but you're actually aware of it. Absolutely. You've mapped the stars of
it. Mm-hmm. How do you say thank you in Wussam? Uh, we say Masavana. And so Masavana was a person,
I was an actual person. Um, I think he was from Madagascar, enslaved, and, um, escaped,
made his way to South Africa, and, um, ended up passing away. And so the word, I took his name
and applied that. So in our home, we say Masavana. And then the response to that is Ashe,
which is, of course, already a word that we have. Yep. So if I say Masavana to my children,
they say Ashe. Or if they say Masavana to me, I say Ashe. So be it. So be it. Listen, I'm just like,
this is the community I'm in. This is incredible. Travis, I hope I make it to Minneapolis on a book
tour, on this book tour, and I hope I get to meet you in person so I can greet you with the Omo.
Omo. Omo. Well, the greeting is Wussam. The greeting is Wussam. What is Omo? Oh,
the response is Omo. Oh, okay. So I'll say Wussam Travis. I'll say Omo. Yeah. Ashe.
Incredible. Thank you so much for sharing this with us. I know so many people here feel so inspired
and so expanded in getting to listen to your journey and your brilliance. So Masavana.
Ashe. Masavana. Ashe. And Tuzazi. Hey, Tuzazi. Absolutely. Tuzazi to you. Tuzazi to you.
Now, I didn't tell you how to spell Tuzazi, though. That's the fascinating part. So here's my younger
son. Tell me how to spell it. Yasi. Come here for a second. This is my youngest son, Yasiel.
Yasiel. And you can try the language with him. Wussam, Yasiel. She said Wussam.
Oh, Omo. Ashe. Ashe. Yasiel, can you teach me how to spell Tuzazi?
T-U. T-U. Go ahead. T-U-B. T-U-B. T-U-B. Um. W-X-Y-B. W-X-Y-B.
Yeah. It actually does look like the word now that I spelled it. Tuzazi, you're beautiful.
Did you know that? She said you're beautiful. Oh, he can't hear you. I got my earphones on.
Oh, that's why he's looking at me like, what is this lady saying? Yeah, yeah. She said you're
beautiful. Oh, thank you. You're welcome. You're welcome. So Tuzazi, it's spelled T-U-Z-W-X-Y-B?
It is. And the reason why is because, um, you know, as in French, they say dublevée,
and I know you speak multiple languages. Um. I zabble. I don't think it's fair to say I speak,
but I, you know, I zabble. Um. In English, we say double U, right? Two U, dublevée. Um. But the U, V,
and Y all have the same origin. And so if you take the T, um, V, I'm sorry, U, V.
W. Um. U, W, T, U, V. So the U, V, and W have the same origin. And so two, T, U, Xi would be X, Y,
and then just the Z. Um. And if you look at the up and down motion of those letters,
uh, it takes the pattern that we all take in life, right? Life is full of ups and downs. And so if you
write it out, T being your beginning, and then Z being your zenith, and then the journey in between
is the U, V, W, X, Y, and Z. Um. And so if we trace it back further, getting back to the,
the phonetic origin of alphabet or the Phoenician origin of the alphabet or the comedic origin of
the alphabet, then we get to the mark, hook, fish, and arrow, which is the deeper, um, photograph
or pictograph of those particular, what will become those letters. Um. And so the mark, hook,
fish, and arrow, where you set your mark, you of course get your hook, you fish,
fish, and you utilize your weapon to protect it. Um. And so that becomes
what we call Tuzazi. But if you were to just write out T-U-V-W-X-Y-Z, it looks like you can't
pronounce that as a word. Hence that those letters being used to, um, describe a feeling that I have
for my family that I just can't quite put into words. And so Tuzazi, or what we, our word for what
in English is called love, because we love everything, right? I love books, some people love music,
some people love traveling, but it's not the same. You love, you say cheese? Yeah. Okay. But it's not
the same. I'm thinking about it right now. But it's not the same love you have for your family, right?
If it's a different type. I'm not, I'm not putting it on levels. I don't know if I love it. You know,
love cheese more. I'm like, I mean.
But the love I have for my family. Cheese be showing up for me in a way that my family don't.
So. Yep. One of you love more. I'm not judging. But the Tuzazi I have for my family is not the same as
the love I have for book. Fair. Fair. Fair. Yes. Well, I'm also going to use for Amanda Land. So
views for Amanda Land is my show that I do Monday. I mean, that I do Wednesdays at 10 a.m. Eastern
on YouTube, Amanda Seals TV. And we have guests. We, the whole point of the show is to contextualize
the news. Right. And, you know, focus on critical thinking skills, et cetera. But we always have a
Level Us Up guest who puts us on to level us up. So Travis Sankofa, formerly known as Travis Smith,
we are absolutely going to be reaching out to you so you can come and teach us a thing or two.
And not just about Wussan, but like, why that even, because you took us on a journey that brought us
there. When I knew we would go, I knew there was something when you started making reference to the
indigenous. Because when people who are not necessarily born into the indigenous community
find out, like, you know, it's like when white people find out about butters. Right. When white
people find out about shea butter and jojoba, they're like, what is going on? Right. And I feel like for
those of us who have been sequestered from all these indigenous teachings, find out about them, it's like,
it's like a whole new world opens up and then you made a whole new world out of that world.
Absolutely. And so, and we need that. We need to be visionaries in this time. Like that's,
if we're going to talk about breaking things down, we have to know how to build things up. Right.
That's for sure.
Absolutely. So thank you. I will be reaching out. Y'all make sure to wish Travis a happy Tuzazi.
Wait, Tuzazi? Tuzazi is goodbye, right? Or is it thank you?
No, Tuzazi is love. Thank you is Mastavanna.
Thank you is Mastavanna. Tuzazi is love. And then how do we say goodbye?
We say Tuzazi when we leave. Okay. That's what I thought. All right. All right. All right. So.
Yep. Yep. Yep. Tuzazi. Oh, Tuzazi to you. I gotta,
I gotta screen record you saying that. You got it. Well, I'm going to post this.
So you can screen record it when I post it. Yeah. Okay. So Mastavanna for, for speaking with us
and sharing with us and for introducing us to your son. And Tuzazi Travis, you have a great evening.
Tuzazi, you too. Thank you.
Tuzazi. I see.
Don't never say I don't give y'all nothing. Don't never give any of you a whole lot of Z in the chat.
Notice the difference though. Like when that man made the Mormonism, how like devilish it was,
like he made up a whole thing and it was like mad discriminatory and whack and self-serving.
Wussam is all about Wussam. Okay. And, and love. Come on, man. Well, golly.
Well, this has been an excellent edition. All of us are like, what did we just experience? What
did we just experience? Yodel lady, you might be going to have to listen back because we had two
incredible guests tonight on what would your ancestors say? Wendegard, trust me, I am taking
your lead and that is actually going to happen. This, um, welcome Pamela, this photographer.
So I want to remind you all that you can support the work that I'm doing. See, this is the type of
work I do. You can support the work that I'm doing by getting your tickets to see what would the
ancestors say on the live stream on November 8th. You can also get a package deal with the, uh,
book and the live stream, uh, with a signed book, sorry, a signed book and the live stream.
And there's also the opportunity to actually be in the studio in LA. Okay. So all of that is happening.
And I got to tell you all go to AmandaSeals.com, get your tickets, uh, go to AmandaSeals.com. You can
also go to AmandaLandExports.com to get your tickets. And, um, but I just got to tell y'all,
you know, this is, these are all like labor of loves and I divested from celebrity. I bought my book
back from Simon and Schuster. And I said, I still need to give these people a book before the year is
out. I still got to give these people a book. So thank you all for supporting. I will be right.
Harriet is strapped because our ancestors are on the main line and they aren't ready to have our backs.
That's why. That's why. All right. So this is the book. Your girl wrote it. Your girl illustrated it.
Your girl wrote a forward. Your girl wrote an additional resources list of films and speeches and
essays and books that you can read to expand your knowledge of the themes that are talked about in
this book. And I also laid the book out on InDesign. So when you see people like how dare AmandaSeals ask for
a hundred percent of her sales, Amanda Seals did a hundred percent of the work. I did a hundred percent
of the work. Okay. So shout out to everybody who's, um, signed on to host me with a, um,
thank you, Mark Forrest Stroud. Anyone who congrats me, who congratulates me on InDesign,
they understand InDesign is, is that it'll break you. InDesign will break you. Um, I had to take naps.
There'll be times where I like when I was trying to figure out how to do page numbers, y'all,
I literally had to take a nap because it was so complicated that I just had to bow out for an
hour and come back to it. My brain was like, give it, let me tap out, tap out. Okay. So thank you,
two girls treasures. Um, so remember the book will be on sale on its own on the eighth. And, um,
um, right now you can also, uh, get you some Malcolm X, the brother Malcolm drop. So for those
who don't know, I also do pins and paper goods, et cetera. And the Malcolm X drop,
the brother Malcolm drop, as I call it is available right now. So you can get the brother Malcolm pin,
the brother Malcolm print, the brother Malcolm, um, the brother Malcolm sticker sheets, the big
ass sticker, et cetera. So all of that is coming at you. So I will see you all tomorrow morning,
10 AM Eastern on YouTube, Amanda Seals TV for yet another edition of views from Amanda land. So make
sure you join me to wake up on the right side of history. Um, people are thinking that I'm wearing a top.
I'm wearing a top.